Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Xiao-Yunzi cannot leave the palace.
I've arranged for you to serve Noble Lady Vertu.
Pin'er will serve Consort Estime.
Vermillion died.
Jade, if you still want to stay in the palace,
I can make arrangements
for you to serve Noble Lady Vertu or Consort Estime.
Jinxi, you were serving the consort dowagers before.
You could return to those duties.
The rest of you
will be assigned other work.
Others can be re-assigned.
But I've made the decision
to follow Your Highness.
After Vermillion's tragic death,
you are the only family I have, My Lady.
I don't want to be separated from you.
Why would you do this to yourselves?
I could have left the palace after I turned 25.
But I didn't.
I have been alone and have no home to return to.
So I am intent on following Your Highness,
just like Jade.
Even in the temple,
I can look after Your Highness.
If you aren't afraid of hardship,
I don't want to part with any of you.
Sourire, is this your only way out?
The longer I stay in the palace,
the more dangerous it will be for the princess.
From now on,
Your Highness will be her mother.
I promise you.
I will treat her as if she were my own daughter.
Longyue is Your Highness's daughter.
Why say "as if" to your own child?
I believe Your Highness will take good care of her.
I know that
you could have entrusted Longyue
to any concubine.
But you had sympathy for me
because I don't have a child to rely on.
I hope Your Highness
will take account of our sisterhood
and take care of Meizhuang for me.
Don't worry, I will.
Your Highness, please go.
It's too painful leaving her.
My Lady,
would you want to take the
jade shoes gifted by His Majesty?
Don't take anything.
Just the necessary clothes.
And Endless Longing, the zither.
Yes, My Lady.
All the awards from His Majesty
are in this cabinet.
Put the lock on.
The Household Department will make an inventory.
The carriage will be here soon.
You should get changed, My Lady.
Please allow us a moment
for Lady Vertu to talk to My Lady.
Be quick. We are on a schedule.
Huan'er.
Please don't worry, Your Highness.
Mr. Zhen's condition has improved a lot.
He can eat and drink normally now.
I believe he will have a full recovery soon.
My father should leave Beijing
as soon as he returns to health，
in case something else goes wrong.
This was also His Majesty's intention.
As soon as your father's health improves,
he will leave Beijing and be sent to
Ningguta.
I know
His Majesty won't change his mind.
It's also good for you to leave.
You will be free, from the palace.
Please take care of yourself, Meizhuang.
I'm afraid we will never be able to
take care of each other again.
When you're gone,
I will be all alone, living a bleak life.
How I wish
I was going with you!
Why would you say that, Meizhuang?
Each day you live in the palace,
you have to keep an eye on
An Lingrong and the Empress.
Don't act on impulse because of me.
The priority is to protect yourself.
Yes.
Dr. Wen,
Meizhuang is alone in the palace,
I entrust her to you.
Please keep her well.
Don't let her fall into any traps.
Your Highness ...
You must also take care of yourself.
I will visit you once I get a chance.
Once I enter the Temple of Pure Dew,
I will be separated from the mortal world.
It would be inappropriate for you to visit.
If you have the intention to help me,
please take care of Longyue
and Meizhuang.
That is my only wish now.
My Lady ...
We shouldn't talk for too long.
Depart.
We have arrived, My Lady.
Mistress, the mountain breeze is chilly in October.
You just gave birth to a child.
It's better to keep warm.
Patrons, did you come from the palace?
Madam Abbess asked us
to bring you in.
Please.
Thank you.
Mistress, you are here.
Thank you for waiting, Madam Abbess.
It’s all right.
My humble monastic name is Jing'an.
Per the decree from the palace,
you will observe Buddhist practice without shaving your head.
Even so,
to practice in the nunnery,
you have to observe the precepts.
Yes.
Since you have entered the nunnery,
you are no longer a concubine in the palace.
You should stay away from the secular world,
and can't use your previous name anymore.
I will give you a name that starts with "Mo",
same as my disciples.
In your eyes I sense some sorrow.
I will name you Mochou.
["Without Worry"]
I appreciate your compassionate intent, Madam Abbess.
You're not supposed to have servants
when practicing in the nunnery.
But I have been informed by the palace
to allow you companions, like
Consort Dowager Serein.
Pardon me. Pardon me.
I meant Venerable Abbess Serene.
You two may practice along with Mistress Mochou.
Thank you, Madam Abbess.
Thanks.
Dew drops can ease the sorrow of the world.
You have left the secular world now.
Let go of your troubles.
This is Prioress Jingbai.
She is in charge of daily matters in the nunnery.
You may ask her for help in the future, if needed.
It's getting late. You should rest for now.
Thank you for your arrangements, Madam Abbess.
Please follow me.
This is the place.
You may clean it up yourself.
Mistress, please sit down.
Sit here for now, My Lady.
I will put away the clothes.
There is nothing to put away.
Just a few changes of clothes.
Your monastic name is so unique, My Lady.
Mochou doesn’t sound like an
ordinary monastic name.
It’s more like a young lady’s name.
Madam Abbess wants to exhort me
to forget about
the sorrows of my previous life now that I am in the nunnery.
Yes.
The most important thing from now on
is to pray day and night
that my parents, Yurao, and Longyue
can have a peaceful life.
This is my only wish.
Mine as well.
What's wrong, My Lady? Your face is so pale.
You recently gave birth.
I'm afraid you are fatigued by the long journey today.
What should we do?
We need to find brown sugar.
You'll feel better after drinking some with hot water.
Don't bother.
How could we find brown sugar right now?
I can endure it.
That is no good.
Illness can never be taken lightly the first month after childbirth.
Otherwise you might suffer from a lifelong condition.
Jade,
you take care of our Mistress.
I will borrow some brown sugar from the nuns next door.
All right.
My Lady, let me help you lie down.
My Prioress, do you have any brown sugar?
Can we borrow some brown sugar?
Prioress Jingbai, is there any brown sugar here?
Mistress Zhen Huan recently gave birth,
and might have caught a cold on the way here.
Do you have any brown sugar we can borrow?
Prioress Jingbai...
The nuns either didn't have
brown sugar or ignored my pleas.
Madam Abbes said earlier that we would be
treated like Consort Dowager Serein.
But now we can't even get ourselves some hot water.
There seems to be an empty room over there.
I wonder which prioress is living there.
I'll keep searching. Jade, take care of her.
My Prioress.
Who are you?
Did you give birth recently?
Yes, it has been seven days.
Why would you bear a child for those stinking men?
Serves you right.
This should be enough to help you.
Don't go out bothering others anymore.
This is over two pounds of brown sugar!
Really?
I always thought monks and nuns have compassionate hearts.
Why are the nuns here so brash and arrogant?
They are just like the people in the palace.
We were ousted from the palace
after my title was removed.
Without influence or power,
it's not surprising for us to be snubbed.
Although that nun seemed cold,
she has a rare warm heart.
The princess is as fair as jade and snow,
just like her mother.
From now on, Longyue's mother is Consort Estime.
I've deprived
Concubine Sourire of her rank and honorary name,
expelled her from the palace,
and sent her to the Temple of
Pure Dew to observe Buddhism.
She gave birth to the princess.
How can she still be so stubborn?
She bid me a lasting farewell.
I wouldn't have forced her to stay.
I don't want the princess to learn the ways
of her mother anyway.
I agree.
Consort Honnête is
already fostering Princess Wenyi.
Consort Estime is also a trustworthy person.
Your Majesty, given Concubine Sourire's departure,
now there are even fewer concubines in the palace.
To complement the joyful news of the princess's birth,
Your Majesty should promote more
Noble Ladies to the rank of Concubine.
Who do you think is suited for promotion?
Noble Lady Délice's father accomplished a great feat,
and they are from a noble family of the Manchu Banners.
She is a suitable candidate.
Don't you think Noble Lady Vertu
should be promoted as well?
Concubine Sourire left the palace
because of her stubborn nature.
As Your Majesty's concubine,
it is most important to be understanding and obedient.
Noble Lady Vertu is also strong-willed.
I don't think she should be promoted for now.
It is your decision.
What's going on?
Why is it so smoky?
Prioress Jingbai was distributing charcoal for the winter,
but nothing was allotted to us.
She only gave us some firewood
to burn into charcoal by ourselves.
How could she do such a thing?
Isn't there charcoal ready for use?
There is.
But Mochou is here to cultivate herself
by His Majesty's decree,
not to be served by us.
Prioress Jingbai,
it will take too long to burn the wood into charcoal.
Our mistress has been frail
since giving birth a month ago.
Can you take that into consideration and
give us a few days' worth of charcoal?
After all, our mistress is here
by His Majesty's decree.
His Majesty's decree?
That's only a line for outsiders.
Don't bother using it on us
here in the temple.
As the saying goes,
"Deceive those above, but not those below."
Do you really think we are fools?
Everyone knows Mochou was expelled from the palace.
Let me offer you another idea.
There are trees on the far side of the mountain.
Go chop your own firewood -
it won't be different from this.
This isn't the palace where you can
get whatever you want.
Mistress Mochou is no longer a concubine.
She should know her place.
My Lady.
It's better to rely on ourselves than others.
I agree.
My Lady, your health has always been delicate.
How can you do such hard labor?
Besides, you have always lived a gentle life.
Regardless of how comfortably I've lived,
it is in the past now.
Besides our usual chores, Prioress Jingbai
has given us so much extra work.
I can't sit idly by and enjoy the fruits of your work.
Mistress, don't touch that.
There is not much we can say
if you put it that way.
But there is one thing.
You're still frail and have not fully recovered yet.
If you have the strength, you can go gather kindling.
Jade and I should do the dirty work
of chopping firewood and burning charcoal.
All right.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace to Imperial Mother.
Rise.
Yes.
Have a seat.
You have been managing the palace affairs on your own.
Don't overwork yourself.
Thank you for your concern, Imperial Mother.
Have Concubine An and Concubine Délice
been serving the Emperor well?
Yes, they have.
That is good.
It's about time to have concubines with
stable temperament by the Emperor's side.
They must be acquiescent as well.
They would hurt His Majesty's feelings
if they behaved like Concubine Sourire.
The past is in the past.
Zhen Huan was deprived of her rank
and expelled.
She will never be able to return.
You should keep an eye on those under your nose.
Don't let anything go wrong.
I will carefully remember your advice, Imperial Mother.
Orchid.
Why is Orchid in your palace, Imperial Mother?
Isn't she supposed to be serving His Majesty?
Orchid was Concubine Sourire’s etiquette instructor.
The Emperor doesn’t want to be reminded of Concubine Sourire.
So he re-assigned her.
I consider her reliable, so I kept her in my service.
By the way,
the Emperor said that a series of blizzards struck the south.
He is afraid it will impact next year’s harvest,
and wants the harem to host a ceremony
to pray for blessings.
What do you plan to do?
We always pray for blessings in Baohua Hall.
However, it may be better to wait for spring
and go to the Temple of Pure Dew.
This will save the cost of inviting
monks and nuns into the palace,
and bringing the concubines with me
will show deep sincerity.
Do you insist on going there?
I will obey your wish, Imperial Mother.
All right then.
You know what is proper.
We will do as you suggest.
Stop!
Prioress Jingbai.
How is the firewood you picked even usable?
You must have found it on the rear of the mountain.
The branches are big but are too moist to burn well.
You originally seemed intelligent...
who would know you are stupid to the bone?
After all, you were a concubine in the palace,
and have no common sense or ability to work.
All you did was enjoy a comfortable life.
My Prioress is right.
Look at this minx. How could she know
how to gather firewood?
All she knows is how to feign her feelings
and make people pity her.
She still thinks she’s in the palace.
I bet she was a minx in the palace
who spent all her time bewitching His Majesty.
Amitabha Buddha.
Go, leave.
I’m irritated just by looking at you.
Go gather two more baskets of firewood.
Otherwise, no dinner for you.
Dinner is about to start. Where are you going?
There is not enough firewood. I’m going to gather more.
You can’t go on an empty stomach.
Go after dinner.
Better not. The earlier I go, the earlier I will return.
You’re not in good health. Let me go with you.
What’s wrong?
She pinched you again, didn’t she?
Don’t you know to fight back when being bullied?
It’s my fault.
I’ll just rub some liniment on it.
Don’t you know you can tell the Abbess?
The less trouble, the better.
Please speak no more of it.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Why have you come so late in the evening?
You may rise.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
I heard that Your Majesty has been busy preparing
for the trip to the Temple of Pure Dew.
I came to see if there is anything
I can help Your Majesty with.
You’re worried because I chose to hold
the ceremony in the Temple of Pure Dew.
Your Majesty has keen judgment.
Dull-witted as I am,
I am, indeed, perplexed by it.
I’m doing this because I know that
His Majesty still has feelings for Zhen Huan.
Zhen Huan has already been banished from the palace.
And her family is exiled to Ningguta.
What's there to worry about?
It's alarming how much His Majesty
cares about Princess Longyue.
Even Orchid has been cast out
from the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
There is no longer a maid directly serving His Majesty.
She is only a maid. It's not a big deal.
Madam Orchid was Zhen Huan's etiquette instructor.
His Majesty did so because he still cares.
He doesn't want to be reminded of Zhen Huan by Orchid.
Just take a look at Lady Vertu.
His Majesty has rarely seen her
since Zhen Huan left the palace.
Even when His Majesty visits Consort Estime,
he won't set foot in Vertu's palace, right next door.
Fortunately, the Zhen family has no relatives in Beijing anymore.
Zhen Huan has no one to rely on,
and won't be able to turn the situation around again.
Be that as it may, I am still not at ease.
Zhen Yuandao is lucky to have survived
the journey to Ningguta.
He is out of our reach now.
We might as well focus on the person right under our noses,
and ensure the soil is pounded down over her.
Your Majesty has great foresight.
We feel incomparably inferior.
Autumn.
Fetch me the Red Jade necklace.
Yes.
Your Majesty.
This is a tributary Red Jade necklace.
The color looks young and vibrant.
It might be too bold for me,
but it suits Concubine Délice very well.
I thank Your Majesty.
The Red Jade smells so good.
It must be scented with the finest fragrances.
I would never give you anything less.
Ever since Huan'er left,
you have been in low spirits, My Lady.
It has been three months.
I am concerned for her situation out there.
If it's possible, I am willing to make a visit on your behalf.
However, the Temple of Pure Dew is a place for nuns.
It would be inappropriate for me to go.
If anyone asks,
just say I sent you there.
I can't leave the Forbidden City.
I hope you can go visit her often.
I'm honored to obey.
Of course, you need to be discreet.
Do not linger there too long.
Yes.
My Lady, your frostbite is flaring up again.
It looks worse this year.
Some things just can't be forgotten
no matter how hard I try.
Just like the frostbite. It comes back every year.
My hands are blistered with frostbite.
Red, green, and purple.
Look, My Lady, the red is coral,
the green is jade,
and the purple is amethyst.
I was a maid doing menial chores
when I first entered the palace.
It's hard to avoid being bullied as a newcomer.
I washed clothes for the Madams in the winter,
and got frostbite all over my hands.
When His Majesty was still a lord,
he was already married to Empress Première.
One time, when she visited the Empress Dowager,
she saw my hands and said, "Poor thing."
"Why are you still washing clothes with
such bad frostbite?"
After that, the Household Department
assigned me to other tasks.
Luckily, I'm experienced in manual labor from that time.
Otherwise, I would not be able to serve you now.
Let me help you.
- Please don't.
- Huan'er.
Dr. Wen.
How can you do such strenuous work?
I'm just a commoner practicing Buddhism.
There's nothing wrong with me working.
Enough. Enough.
The water is enough for today.
For today?
You have to work this hard every day?
We do everything ourselves.
This is nothing.
My Lady has helped chop firewood, boil water,
wash clothes, and cook meals every day.
It's not hard for Jinxi and me,
since these are our duties.
However, My Lady's hands have suffered.
It's nothing.
Let me see. Let me see.
Dr. Wen, please allow me.
Here. Cover the wounds.
Let me do this. Let me.
How has Meizhuang been since I left the palace?
How's Longyue?
You promised me that
you would look after them for me.
They are both doing well.
Lady Vertu is worried about you
and asked me to visit you.
I am relieved to know they are doing well.
I don't have other skills.
But I try my best to look after those you put into my care.
I thank you.
You need not thank me.
That's all the medicine I brought today.
You can make do with it for now.
I will bring you better medicine the next time.
Thank you.
Don't dawdle!
Be quick. Clean up the temple inside and out.
What took you so long?
You must be loafing around.
Bring over the barrel.
Go clean the floor of the main hall.
Mopping the floor is the greatest torment.
You can't straighten your back or raise your head.
Besides, the main hall is quite large.
After a few hours,
your whole body will be aching.
Jingbai knows well how to discipline
people with such work.
I heard that in a few days
there will be a ceremony praying for the
imperial princesses and princes.
Mochou gave birth to a princess.
Will she participate in the ceremony as well?
She is a banished wretch, inferior to us.
How could she deserve to pray?
That's right.
Jinxi, I'm fine.
It's me.
Noble Prince Guo.
I came too late.
When did you come back?
Three days ago. His Majesty summoned me back.
This is not a good place to chat.
May I speak to you privately?
I feel guilty for not having expressed my
gratitude to you in person.
I was just doing the right thing,
and I'm ashamed for not being able to make a difference.
I will be even more embarrassed
if you insist on thanking me.
I never wished to harm anyone
yet I was banished.
You spoke up for my family
and were sent away to Shengjing.
We caused you such trouble in the past few months.
Don't say that.
His Majesty treats me the same as before,
and I still hold my rank. Nothing is different.
Don't be concerned for me.
I went to Shengjing for leisure,
just like when I traveled around
central Sichuan previously.
To "reflect on my fault" was only an excuse,
not real.
Still, you were implicated by my family...
If you continue saying so,
I won't dare tell you why I came here today.
Please go ahead, Your Lordship.
I went into the palace two days ago
and saw someone by accident.
So I painted a portrait and brought it here.
I wonder if you can comment on
my techniques and offer some advice.
I'm not good at "red and green painting."
How would I be able to critique
Your Lordship's techniques?
This is Consort Estime.
This is Meizhuang.
This is...
I painted this portrait the first time
I met Princess Longyue
to show my affection for her as my niece.
She has grown so much
in such a short time.
Children always grow particularly fast.
I heard that Princess Longyue
will celebrate her first birthday soon.
I assume you must want to know
how she is doing
as you are her birth mother.
This painting is better than thousands of words.
I thank Your Lordship.
I adore Princess Longyue,
and my humble painting is passable.
How about this?
I will paint a portrait of her every few months
and bring it for you to comment on.
What do you think?
Thank you.
In front of us is Misty Mountain,
where my Cooling Terrace is.
I stay there for over ten days every month.
If you need help in the future, just send someone there.
I will definitely try my best to help you.
I'm grateful for seeing a painting of Longyue.
There is nothing else I want.
Actually, I need your help with something.
There will certainly be a banquet
for Longyue's first birthday.
I would like to ask you to lend me a hand for that event.
As her uncle, I need to send her some clothes as gifts.
But the seamstresses in my residence are not skilled enough.
So, my apologies, but I must trouble you for this.
Really?
Can I really make clothes for Longyue?
You are her mother.
The clothes you make will surely
be the most comfortable
and to her liking.
Here are Longyue's measurements.
Five days before her birthday I will be
here to meet you and pick up the clothes.
It's still early so you don't have to rush.
Longyue is sweet and adorable
and seems very close to you.
Exactly.
I heard that Longyue was always hungry
when she first came here.
Consort Estime was so angry that she punished the nursemaid.
Even though Longyue had another nursemaid later,
Her Highness insisted on personally
taking care of the princess day and night.
How could they not be close?
The princess is closest to Your Majesty.
Look, although she’s in my arms,
her little eyes are fixed on Your Majesty.
Yes, she is looking at me.
Children always look like their parents.
The princess looks at Your Majesty
as if she is looking in a mirror.
She has my eyebrows and nose.
Her other features are prettier than mine.
Yes, Princess Longyue’s mouth and chin
look so much like Concubine Sourire.
They are almost identical.
Who did you say?
I… I said the princess looks like her mother.
The princess only has one mother. Nobody else.
May peace be restored in Your Majesty.
I recognize my fault.
I will never misspeak again.
Peace to Your Majesty and My Ladies.
All rise.
Yes.
How are the preparations for the ceremony going?
Everything is ready.
Please come offer incense in the main hall, Your Majesty.
Please lead the way, Madam Abbess.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.